[MUSIC]
控制型一錯誤率
In this lecture we will revisit Type 1 errors and we'll take a closer look
這一講要回顧型一錯誤率以及仔細檢視
at one problematic aspect of Type 1 error control.
控制型一錯誤率會遇到的問題
Where we see that in the scientific literature,
閱讀科學文獻時
people are sometimes inflating their error rates by certain practices that lead them
有時會發現作者利用一些手段誇大錯誤率
to conclude that there is an effect when there is actually no effect,
以比實際設定的顯著水準更高的百分比
at a much higher percentage than the alpha level that they've decided upon.
做出效果存在的的虛假結論
And it's important to not make this mistake yourself.
所以我要告訴你如何避免犯這樣的錯誤
So just to revisit, the Type 1 error is the situation when you say that there is
復習一下：型一錯誤率是宣稱發現效果，實際沒有的錯誤
something when there's actually nothing that's going on.
So you're concluding that there is a true effect when the null
也就是虛無假設為真，結論卻宣稱有效果存在
hypothesis is actually true.
So typically, we set an alpha level at 0.05%, which means that
通常會設定顯著水準為0.05%
in 5% of the studies we do, in the long run, where the null hypothesis true,
也就是做過的一系列研究裡有5%顯示虛無假設為真
we will say that there is an effect to be observed, but we'll be wrong.
卻錯誤地做出效果存在的結論
So this is a choice.
結論如何只是一種選擇
You can set this alpha level at any level that you want.
顯著水準可以設定在任何你滿意的水準
And in physics it's very typical to use the 5 sigma level, which is this very,
物理學的慣例是設定在5個標準差
very low alpha value that you see below.
這是目前所知最嚴格的水準
Now one problematic aspect that inflates the Type 1 error rate, so
導致型一錯誤率膨脹的一種問題
that increases the number of times that you will say that there is an effect
是進行多重比較，而導致犯下結論有效果
when there's actually nothing going on, is when you make multiple comparisons.
實際卻沒有效果的次數增加
So you collect some data and you do one test and another test and
這發生在你把收進來的資料做了各種不同的比較
another test, so this is a multiple testing situation.
And if you do this, the probability of saying that something is going on
多重比較會讓型一錯誤率膨脹超過5%
somewhere inflates well beyond the 5% level.
Let's look at a situation where we perform an ANOVA and this is a 2x2x2 ANOVA.
拿這個2乘2乘2的變異數分析舉例
So we have two factors times two factors times two factors.
這裡有三個2階層的因子
In this situation, you actually have three main effects that you can test for.
所以要分析的有三個主要效果
Three two-way interactions, and
one three-way interaction, with totals
三個二階交互作用，以及一個三階交互作用
to seven tests that you could perform just
based on this one study that you've done.
總共七道分析要同時進行
In this case the, Type 1 error rate,
if you do all of these tests and you say,
那麼分析結果出來後，實際的型一錯誤率會是怎麼樣呢？
Well look, something happened over here,
let's interpret this, is actually much higher than 5%.
簡單地說，實際是大於5%
You can see that the Type 1 error rate of stating that there is something in one of
因為七道分析的型一錯誤率是乘冪的關係
these seven tests is 1-(0.95) to the power of 7.
以投影片的公式計算會得到真正錯誤率是30%
In total this is actually a 30% error rate.
So you see this is quite substantial.
如果不注意事情就大條了
The probability of saying there's something when there's nothing is
因為30%比5%大了五倍
much higher than the 5%.
So this is one situation where you have to think more clearly about
這個例子是一種分析人員必須仔細考慮的常見情況
what you're doing and what you're testing.
To make sure that you control the Type 1 error rate and
這時必須確認並控制真正的一錯誤率
to prevent it from being inflated.
避免犯錯的機率過度膨脹
Now this is a graph where you can see the probability
這張圖描繪型一錯誤率與分析次數之間的關係
of a Type 1 error given the amount of tests that you do.
And you can see that there's a steep line here.
兩者的關係呈現一道陡升的曲線
It's really increasing.
The number of tests that you do, the more often, the higher the probability that
你要做的分析越多，犯下結論宣稱有效果
you'll say that there's something when there's nothing.
實際沒有效果的錯誤機率越高
And with about 60 tests or something you have a really, almost always something
如果有60道分析且都有顯著結果
will turn out to be statistically significant just due to random variation.
已經可說是隨機變異造成的
This is the example that we looked at before.
之前曾經提過這個例子
This is the 2x2x2 ANOVA where we have seven tests and we test everything.
現在用剛剛提的變異數分析來談分析的狀況
Now in this graph, you can see the vertical line,
圖左邊有一條靠著垂直線的柱子
the graph on the side that's saying the Type 1 error rate.
代表符合預期的型一錯誤率
So all the p-values smaller than 0.05.
也就是說小於0.05的p值有這麼多
And you can see that this should be at the level of the horizontal line.
接著看另一條接近下邊界的水平線
So the horizontal line is the Type 1
代表這個例子裡超過型一錯誤率的p值合理最低數目
error rate that you should expect in this situation.
But you see that the actual observed Type 1 error rate is much,
仔細看就會發現實際超過的數目多於預期
much higher because we are doing many, many different tests.
這是因為多重比較未做控制的緣故
You can control this Type 1 error rate.
實際的型一錯誤率是可以控制的
And you can do this if you design your study well and
只要仔細考慮設計條件
you change the alpha level based on some considerations.
並且慎重改變顯著水準就好
So how can you do this?
要怎麼做呢？
How can you control the Type 1 error
rate to prevent this inflation?
如何做才能避免實際的型一錯誤率膨脹？
The most common way that you can do this,
最常用的方法是Bonferroni校正程序
the easiest way is the Bonferroni correction.
It's called the Bonferroni correction but
雖然很多書寫這個名字
a better name might be the Dunn Correction.
更好的稱呼應該是Dunn校正程序
So, this is Professor Dunn, who actually came up with this idea.
因為這是由Dunn教授提出的方法
And when she did, she said, well,
她曾謙虛地表示
I cannot find anything in the scientific literature that uses this before.
我在之前的文獻找不到相同的方法
And it might be so simple that people just didn't think about it.
可能只是沒有人想到而已
So that's one of the strengths of this Bonferroni correction.
這話道出Bonferroni校正程序的特色：簡潔
It's so remarkably simple to control your error rates, that, well,
這個方法真的簡潔到Dunn教授發表前沒人注意到
until it was discovered by Professor Dunn, nobody had actually come up with it.
But, it's very easy to do.
因為做法真的很簡單
In this case, the alpha level that you'll use isn't 0.05,
需要使用這個方法的場合，顯著水準絕對不是0.05
or whatever you set it to, for a single test, it's the alpha level,
或者說每個分析的顯著水準必須要以分析的數目均分
divided by the number of tests that you do.
So let's say that you do two tests, you'll divide the 0.05, your overall alpha level,
比方說現在要做兩個分析，每個分析的顯著水準
by 2, and have a 0.025 alpha level for each individual test.
是0.05除以2，也就是0.025
In the case of the you will actually divide your alpha level by seven,
所以變異數分析的例子就要除以7
for example.
Alternatively, you can multiply the p-value by the number of tests.
也可以把分析得到的p值乘以分析數目
And it's exactly the same and
then you use the 0.05 alpha level for
看看有沒有那個分析超過了0.05
each specific test.
If we take this latter approach and we plot the p-value distribution, when we
使用後一種方法校正p值
have applied the Bonferroni correction to the same situation we had before,
再繪出p值次數分配圖
you see this very peculiar distribution of p-values.
會發現分配與前一張圖完全不同
In this case, you see that the alpha
level is exactly controlled.
經過精確控制型一錯誤率之後
You see in the bottom left there's this Type 1 error rate which is actually
實際小於0.05的p值數量
at 5% of the total number of stimulations in this case.
是在合理的次數限制之內
Due to the multiplication of the p-values,
we see that there is a bar
因為校正的關係，也導到許多p值大於1
on the right side of this graph that's
completely going through the roof.
這讓最右邊的柱子超出圖片邊界
Most of the p-values actually here, so we multiplied all these p-values and
許多分析結果的p值實際大於1
a lot of them become really, really high or actually one.
才會導致往邊界之外集中的現象
But at least the number of times that we'll say that there's something when
不過分析數目只是未知其他條件時
there's nothing is nicely controlled in this situation.
所能採取的控制手段
We have to control not just
the single test that we do but
如果可知同族錯誤率(family error rate)
what is known as
the familywise error rate.
就不能把每個分析看成各自獨立的
You have to control for
同族的分析必須整體考慮，才不會犯下型一錯誤
all tests that will lead you to say that there is something when there is nothing.
In a situation where we
have seven tests and
變異數分析的例子有7道分析
you will take any test as an indication
that something is going on, well,
以同族錯誤率來看，每一個都不能獨立看待
the family, in this case, is seven tests.
But you could also say,
另一方面
well arguably, I didn't do a 2x2x2 ANOVA
because I was interested in main effects.
我可以只對主要效果有興趣
You're typically interested
in an interaction somewhere,
也可以只對一種二階交互作用
maybe a two-way interaction or
a three-way interaction.
或三階效互作用的分析有興趣
So in this case you would say,
此時「同族」的概念是其中有興趣的四道分析
well, there are actually only four
tests that I'm really interested in.
此時「同族」的概念是其中有興趣的四道分析
This is my family and therefore I'll
divide my alpha level by these four tests.
所以合理的顯著水準應該除以4
Now sometimes you have a very
specific prediction and
若是你有獨特的預測
you don't really need to use
a Bonferroni correction.
並不需要使用Bonferroni校正
If there's only one thing you're
interested in, like research Wahlberg
好比馬克華柏格在「燃燒鬥魂」裡的台詞
says here, if you are only interested
in one girl, there's no comparison.
”如果你只鐘情一名女子，那沒有什麼好比的“
If you're only interested
in one statistical test,
如果你只鐘情一道統計分析
then you don't need to
adjust your alpha level.
那沒有必要調整顯著水準
If you're saying, I'm actually only
interested in the three-way interaction,
好比說你只有興趣分析三階交互作用
then that's the only test you'll do.
只要做這道分析就好
And the only situation where you'll say
this indeed supports my hypothesis, and
分析結果若真的符合預期
you don't need to control
your alpha level any further.
也沒有必要調整顯著水準
In this situations, it make sense to
write down your prediction before you it.
唯一注意的時你要在做分析前先寫下預測
And later on we'll talk about
preregistration as a way to control error
之後在談到「預先註冊」時會提到
rates and write down what the alpha level
is and the tests that you want to do.
分析前註記顯著水準是很重要的
It turns out that the Bonferroni correction is slightly conservative.
Bonferroni校正是稍微保守的方法
You can do a little bit better.
還有其他可行的方法
In practice it won't matter so often.
儘管沒有太多人常用
But given that we use computational tools to calculate these corrections most of
不過別忘這這門課已經介紹很多計算工具
the time, why not use the slightly more efficient version?
為什麼不認識其他方法呢？
This is called Holm correction.
為你介紹Holm校正程序
In this case, you order your p-values' rank.
首先把手上的p值由低至高排序
You inverse the rank order and you say which is the lowest p-value and
接著從最大的p值給予第一位，再給第二位
the second lowest, the third lowest.
第三位直到最小的p值
And you multiply the p-value by the inversed rank order to get
再把每個p值與位階相乘，就會得到校正的p值
a corrected p-value.
So you see that for the lowest p-value in this situation,
這個例子的最小p值(0.001)乘於其位階4
when we do four tests, we actually multiply this very low p-value by 4,
得到的校正p值是0.004
for the second lowest we multiply it by 3, etc.
第二小的p值就是乘以3，依此類推
The benefit is clear in the last line here, where we have the 0.032,
好處是最大的p值校正後依然為原始p值相同
the p-value that we've observed.
But this is the last that we want to test.
而這正是最後做判斷用的p值
In this case, the inversed rank order is 1,
因為最大值的位階由1起算
so actually we don't have to correct for it anymore.
等於不必再去校正這個p值
So this is the p-value we can interpret at a 0.05 level.
並且能以顯著水準0.05做判斷
In this case, this can be considered statistically significant.
所以這個值0.032是達到統計顯著
Whereas if we would use a Bonferroni correction,
如果使用Bonferroni校正程序
this would no longer be statistically significant.
這個值就不會顯著(alpha = 0.025)
Now this is a graph visualising the Holm's corrected p-value distribution.
同樣地把Holm校正的p值繪成次數分配圖
You can see it's slightly different than the Bonferroni correction.
會發現與Bonferroni的次數分配不大一樣
But again, the p-values are 5% of the time, they fall under the 0.05 level and
偍是大致上低於顯著水準的p值只有全部的5%
the Type 1 error rate is adequately controlled.
所以型一錯誤率有被合理控制
So we talked about multiple testing and
接著我們換個角度談多重比較如何造成顯著水準的膨脹
this is one situation where you can inflate your alpha level.
Another widely used, problematic research
practice is known as optional stopping.
這種有問題的操作被稱為「選擇性停止」
In this case you collect some data.
比方現在收集一批資料
You analyze the data.
做了分析
And you do the statistical test.
而且跑了統計檢定
And you see whether the data is statically significance or not.
檢查這筆資料有沒有達到顯著
Let's say you interested whether the p-value is smaller than 0.05.
看一看關切的效果p值有沒有小於0.05
If this is not the case, you collect more people.
若沒有達成，就再收集更多資料
You have additional observations.
因此最後分析的結果包含額外資料
This is quite common practice in many, many research areas.
許多論文的結果都常見到這個狀況
And it sounds like it's a good idea, right?
這聽起來很平常，但是正確的嗎？
It sounds like you should want to do this,
好像大家都是這樣做的
because it's a very efficient way to collect data.
因為這樣比較能有效控管收集成本
If you look at the data and it's already statistically significantly,
若是收集不到一半的資料就有統計顯著
what's the use of continuing on?
要不要繼續收集資料呢？
Regrettably, if you don't control your error rates in this situation,
很不幸地，如果這個時候沒有仔細控制
this actually inflates the Type 1 error rate.
就會導致型一錯誤率的膨脹
So even though this is something that you might want to do, you can do it, but you
有時基於現實條件，中途停止是無可厚非
have to do it the right way by controlling the Type 1 error rates in this situation.
依然還是要妥善控制型一錯誤率
Let's take a look at how you can do this.
我們來看有什麼做法
Now first, let's take a closer look at the problematic aspect of it.
首先看看問題出在那裡
If you do this often enough, then formally,
如果你有豐富的分析資料經驗
using this approach will always lead to a statistically significant result.
並且經常用這種方法獲得顯著結果
Sometimes you have to look at the data 100,000 times, so
當然如果要分析的資料多達十萬筆
it might not be very practical.
這種方法可能並不實用
But formally, as long as you continue looking at your data, and
不過通常只要你中途分析資料
nothing is going on, you will have 100% success rate.
都可以百分之百獲得顯著結果
So in terms of good research practices, I would not recommend it, but
以良好的研究操作來說，我不會建議你這麼做
it is a practice that will give you a guaranteed result 100% of the time.
但是任何研究用這種方法都可以獲得統計顯著
Now, obviously, it will hugely inflate your error rate, so
從稍早的說明，已知如此會膨脹型一錯誤率
that's not what we want to do.
是學習這門課要避免的狀況
Let's take a look at how we can do this the correct way.
我們來看看要怎麼導正這個問題
In this graph we see the distribution of p-values when we're using
這張圖是模擬中途停止分析得到的p值次數分配
optional stopping.
In this simulation we've looked at the data five times.
模擬條件是中途停止五次
There's no true effect, so we should observe the uniform p-value distribution.
實際沒有存在效果，理應得到均勻的p值分配
But you can see there's this very weird peak on the left side of the graph.
但是圖中左側有個詭異的高峰
And there are way more p-values statistically significant
表示顯著的p值數量比合理情況的多很多
than there should be.
We have, by looking at the data repeatedly,
中停分析數次，容易獲得一些接近顯著水準的p值
sort of scratched away some of the nearly significant p-values and
pulled them just below the significance threshold.
長久以往讓這類p值越聚越多
What we can do is use a technique that's called sequential analysis.
我們能用序列分析修正這個問題
In sequential analysis you can look at the data repeatedly,
序列分析能保持型一錯誤率
while controlling your Type 1 error rate.
又能讓你做中停分析
You're using something that's very similar to a Bonferroni correction but
這種方法像是效率提昇的Bonfrroni校正程序
it's actually even more efficient.
In principle, you could just
use a Bonferroni correction.
原則上可以只用Bonfrroni校正
You can just decide just how often you want to look at the data,
只要先決定要中途停止幾次
let's say four times, and then divide the alpha level by four.
比方說四次，那就等於有4道分析
That would be perfectly fine.
Bonfrroni校正就派上用場
But the sequential analysis approach is slightly more flexible and more efficient.
只不過序列分析使用更有彈性的方法
Now you don't have to read this.
這張投影片上的文字不必仔細讀
The font is too small to be read by you, but I will explain what's going on.
因為字太小，我解釋給你聽就好
This is a quote from a paper by Wald, in 1945,
這段來自Wald於1945年發表的論文
where he introduces the sequential ratio probability test.
這篇論文介紹序列機率比分析
This is a new statistical tool at this moment and
這段說明當時這是一種新的統計分析技術
when he was examining it, was 1943.
實際上1943年Wald就已經完成
This was during the second World War.
當時二次大戰尚未結束
He had done the math and
Wald整日埋首研究數學
said, this is actually a very efficient way to collect data.
有一天發現一種有效收集資料的方法
And they wanted to use this in the war effort to test, for example, ammunition.
能運用於測試子彈良率的分析
Every now and then they had to do a test, is this working correctly or not?
這種測試經常要做，但能不能知道結果正確嗎？
And using this sequential approach made them much more efficient,
使用序列分析讓測試更有效率
which is why the National Defense Committee said we cannot share this
因為有軍事價值，當時被五角大廈列為機密
knowledge at this moment.
Because if you would publish this in the scientific literature, our enemies,
如果1943年就被發表出來
in this case the Germans and the Japanese, would also discover this technique and
讓德國或日本軍方發現的話
use it and become much more efficient.
有可能會使用這技術
So this is the explanation about Wald saying that he only published it in 1945,
這是後來Wald解釋為何在1945年發表的說法
after the war, because this was deemed such an efficient technique
因為他很自豪自已的發明
that the US government said you cannot share it with the enemy during wartime.
卻被美國政府以軍事命令限制發表
Now this is interesting, right?
很有趣的傳聞對吧
So there is this technique that correctly controls error rates and
這種方法能控制分析錯誤率
that will make you much more efficient.
又能讓資料收集更有效率
But at the same time, we're not using it very often.
不過現在這種方法還未普遍使用
There are many researchers slightly hesitant to use statistical approaches.
多數研究者有點抗拒參考統計指標做資料收集
But my prediction is that his will be used more and more in the future, just because
不過我預測這種方法未來會有越來越多人使用
it's a very efficient way to collect data while controlling error rates.
這是一套收集資料時能有效控制分析錯誤率的方法
If you want to set an alpha level using this sequential approach, you can do so
序列方法有許多做法幫你設定顯著水準
in many different ways.
The easiest, that I will give an example for in the slide, is that you
最簡單的一種就像這張投影片的範例
lower your alpha level to the same level for each time that you look at the data.
只要每次中途停止就降低顯著水準
But as I said, there's much more flexibility that's possible here.
不過還有其他更有彈性的做法
You can spend your alpha level over each look at the data in any way you like.
比方使用你偏好的方式疊加每次分析的顯著水準
You can only have a very, very strict alpha level at the beginning.
只要在一開始設定最嚴格的顯著水準
Don't spend too much of your alpha level and
不必每次重新設定顯著水準
then later on use most of it when you have the largest sample size.
序列演算會指示達到最大樣本數的顯著水準
But you can also spread it out evenly over every look depending on what you want.
另一方面也能演算任何中停時機的顯著水準
The easiest way is using a Pocock boundary.
最簡單的方式是演算Pocock邊際
This is very similar to just dividing the number of looks by, or
這種方法很像拿顯著水準直接除以中停次數
the alpha level, by the number of looks.
It's slightly more efficient, which is why, if you look twice,
只要注意看就會發現這方法的效率關鍵
you have a slightly higher threshold than 0.025,
像是兩次分析設定的閾限比0.025稍高
which you would have with the Bonferroni correction.
很像Bonferroni校正程序的結果
But you can see it's pretty close.
但是兩者的結果相當接近
So these are the thresholds that you would use if you look at the data twice or
這裡也列出中停三次,四次中的閾值
three times or four times.
Well, something like that is typically sufficient in a study that you do.
這些數值足以應付多數研究的需要
Remember that this was the optional stopping p-value
這張也是因為中停分析導致錯誤率膨脹
distribution where the error rate is inflated.
而形成的p值次數分配
So we see way more p-values just below 0.05 in this case.
來看看序列分析如何校正小於0.05的p值
Now if we use the corrected p-values based on the Pocock stopping rule,
經過Pocock中停演算校正p值之後
the distribution still looks a little bit peculiar.
次數分配還是有些怪異
But in this case the error is rate exactly 0.05.
但是現在的p值是真正小於0.05
So this is one approach to control errors.
以上是一種中停分析的校正方法
We talked about multiple comparisons using Bonferroni approach.
稍早提到校正多重比較的Bonferroni程序
You can use sequential tests and control error rates using, for example,
當然也可使用如Pocock等序列分析控制顯著水準
the Pocockl boundary.
There are many different ways in which you can control error rates.
還有很多我未介紹的方法
And an alternative to this, in recent years,
近幾年興起另一種取向
is not controlling the error rate itself, but the false discovery rate.
不是控制顯著水準，而是控制分析錯誤率
I just want to point out that this is possible if you're interested in this and
特別提醒這種方法是用在分析的資料
you're working in field where you're doing many, many,
要進行海量的統計比較分析
many different tests, huge number of statistical test.
Then this is a very interesting
approach to consider.
如果你真的有興趣
And this is a paper by Benjamini &
Hochberg that you might want to read.
可以找Benjamini與Hochberg的論文來看
I'm not going to go into too much detail but it's an interesting perspective to
我不會說明太多細節，只是告訴你
learn about, if it's relevant for your research question.
這種方法可能適用你的研究
(Neuro science?)
Now remember that there's nothing
special about this 5% threshold.
再次提醒5%顯著水準不是鐵則
You can increase it, you can decrease it.
你可以視情況增加或減低
As I said before,
像之前提過
it's up to you to determine how this balance should be struck.
根據研究者要達到什麼樣的平衡決定
If you want to use a more strict error control or a more lenient version,
不管採用較嚴格或較寬鬆的錯誤率控制
that's perfectly fine.
都是合理的
In recent years, we've seen a lot of people worried about
最近幾年，學術圈內興起檢討
the way that people control their Type 1 errors.
多數研究者控制型一錯誤率的方法
And there's some idea that the error rate in the scientific literature is inflated.
一些偵測科學文獻裡錯誤率被低估的方法不斷出現
In due, this is because people want to use more flexibility in the way that they
歸根究底，是許多研究者在分析資料時
analyze their data.
採用太多彈性措施
Looking at the sequential approach is one way in which you can actually have this
使用序列分析方法可以讓你保留彈性
flexibility but you can be more efficient in the same time.
又能有效控制型一錯誤率
In other ways,
另一方面
you have to decide very clearly on which specific tests you are interested in.
你必須決定你真正想檢驗的統計分析
And defining these tests before you collect the data will also make
在收集資料前定義清楚如何使用這些分析
it efficient to control the error rate.
能讓你真正有效控制型一錯誤率
In essence, what I'm saying is that whatever you do, if you set an error rate
這一講所提是最基本的原則，在實作中
for yourself, it's very important to make sure that it's not inflated.
不讓型一錯誤率膨脹是最重要的
If you let it inflate,
如果不小心沒控制好
you will fool yourself much more often than you think you're doing.
你犯下愚弄自已錯誤的機會將比想像的高
[MUSIC]
影片結束